Before we dive straight to the entire materials, I would  to show you how to effectively operate the course.
First things first, one of the most important fact is that this course has been adapted for playback at 1.25
or even 1.5 speed alright?
To enable this option you need to go over  there, click here and just consider choosing the speed 1.25 or even 1.5.
Below our course window we have our different tabs.
The first one is the overview, here you can find the information about the entire course, alright, so there if I go  here and click show more, there you have the description, the features, about me and everything  there, ok?
Next we have the space called Q&A, where you can ask your questions or just search for the answers for already explained topics.
I try to respond there as soon as possible, but it can take maximum 48 hours, alright?
Then we have the notes, where you can just leave the note in specific part of the lecture, alright?
Next the section announcements, where you can find a lot of useful information that we are sharing with you.
for example our best product recommendations for you and there you have entire information  now.
At the  side of the page you have the entire course content with the specific chapters and lectures, alright?
And the most important fact is that there you have the resources, so this is the space where I will provide for you the links, the files to download etc.
Afterwards, we have the options in our window, so we already covered the playback rate alright, at the  side we have the transcript so we can check what will be in this lecture, the captions alright, so there we have a lot of different languages, then we have the settings when we can change the quality of the video or download the lecture when it is possible.
Sometimes it is, sometimes it's not, alright?
And then the last one option to go over with the full screen.
And the last one option at the  top corner is to leave a review.
I don't recommend to do this when you're starting the course.
Just take your time and leave it when you would  and you will consume a lot of materials, alright?
and I really appreciate it because it helps me to understand what I'm doing great and what not, alright?
So if you would , please leave me your honest review.
So that we have it.
In this lecture we covered how to operate the course, therefore let's now go straight forward to the materials.